（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）ああ
Motivation
What's wrong, Yukko?
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）
どうしたの？ ゆっこ
I can't summon the motivation to do anything.
（祐子）
いろいろ やる気が出なくて
What are you talking about?
（みお）何 言ってんの？
私たち高校生なんだよ
We're high school students, you know.
It's the start of a new term.
新学期なんだよ
Motivation is something that comes out naturally once you start doing it.
やる気なんて
やれば自然に出てくるもんだよ
The motivation to do something before actually doing it won't come out.
その やるまでの
やる気が出ないんだよ
How do I get motivated to do
something before I actually start doing it?
やるまでの やる気を出すには
どうすりゃいいの？
The motivation to do something before actually doing it?
やるまでの やる気か…
Hm...
Anyway, just do it!
とにかく やるっきゃない！
All right!
よっしゃあ
I just want to stay as a simple-minded idiot.
Shinonome Institute
Professor! It's about time you woke up.
（東雲(しののめ)なの）はかせ
そろそろ起きてください
Nichijou 01
And... there!
よっと
（はかせ）フワア… おはよう
Good morning...
What are you doing?
何してるの？
Today's breakfast will be fried fish.
今日の朝ごはんは焼き魚ですよ
Eh?!
（はかせ）ええっ！ オムライス…
I want omelette-rice!
Didn't you have that yesterday?
昨日 食べたじゃないですか
Fish contain lots of nutrients, you know!
お魚は栄養が
たくさん入ってるんですよ
（はかせ）不満
Stop being picky and eat everything,
（なの）好き嫌いしないで
何でも食べないと大きく…
otherwise you won't grow bigger- Ah!
（なの）あっ
（猫）ニャッ！
Um, that's our important breakfast, so...
あの それは
大切な朝ごはんなので…
（ネジが緩む音）
（猫）ニャッ！
Ah, no, it's not like that!
いや 違うんです！
これは 決して―
This isn't anything robotic at all!
ロボット的なものでは
なくてですね
Um, this is...
ええと その… ああっ
Ah, it ran away.
（はかせ）あっ 逃げた
（なの）えっ
（なの）ああ… 待ってえ
Wait up!
Have a safe trip.
いってらっしゃい
ハア ハア
Perhaps that cat is also having a hard time?
（なの）もしかしたら
あの猫も困っているのかな？
ああっ ぶつかるう！
Ah, I'm gonna crash!
Kokeshi
Akabeko
Salmon
（みお）あーあ
Mio-chan, selamat pagi!
TL note: Indonesian for "good morning".
みおちゃん  スラマッパギー！
Ah Yukko, good morning!
ああ ゆっこ  おはよう
What should I do, I forgot to bring my student ID...
どうしよう
学生章 着け忘れてきちゃったよ
Huh?
（祐子）あれ？
スラマッパギ 素通り？
She ignored my selamat pagi?
I won't be called upon by the seniors, right?
（みお）上級生に
呼び出されたりしないよね？
If that happens,
そういうときは―
saying "I'm a third year student!" should be enough, don't you think?
“私は３年生だ！”って
言っちゃえばいいんじゃない？
That won't solve anything.
何の解決にも なってないじゃん
（ごう音）
（みお）うん？ 何？
What?
Thunder?
雷？ 晴れてるのに
Even though the weather's clear?
It might suddenly start pouring down, you know!
いきなり降ってくるかもよ？
夕立とか ひょうとか
A shower or a hailstorm...
A kokeshi came down.
（祐子）こけしが降ってきた
A-Are you all right, Yukko?
（みお）だ… 大丈夫？ ゆっこ
（祐子）
うう… まさかの こけしだよ
Who would've thought that a kokeshi would come down?
What a surprise!
ビックリした
どっから落ちてきたんだろう
I wonder where it fell from...
I don't know...
分かんないよお
But it's extremely unlikely that you'd get hit by a kokeshi in your lifetime!
でも 人生の中で―
こけしに当たるなんて
なかなか ないからね
Those people are rare, you know.
めったにないでしょ？
そんな人
I don't think they exist.
（みお）まず いないよ
It might actually mean that luck is with me!
逆にツイてるかも
Luck is not with me...
（祐子）ツイてねえ…
Yukko, are you okay?
（みお）ゆっこ  大丈夫？
An Akabeko of all things...
まさかの赤べこだよ
Akabeko...
赤べこ…
I'm wrong, it's not that luck is not with me.
違う ツイてないんじゃない
We should just think of it this way, Mio-chan...
こう考えればいいんだよ
みおちゃん
I should be happy that I wasn't hit by raw food.
当たったのが
なま物じゃなくてよかった って
Thinking like that, the small mercy amongst the misfortune-
そう考えれば
不幸中の幸い って…
It's a salmon!
シャケだあ！
Tokisada Prefectural High School
Morning!
（月夜野(つきよの)）おはよう
Good morning.
（中之条 剛(なかのじょうつよし)）
おはようございます
Ah, Mai-chan, good morning.
あっ 麻衣(まい)ちゃん おはよう
Selamat pagi!
スラマッパギー！
Morning.
（水上(みなかみ)麻衣）おはよう
What are you reading, Mai-chan?
麻衣ちゃん  何 読んでるの？
A real estate information magazine.
不動産の情報誌
Eh?
（みお）
えっ 麻衣ちゃん 引っ越すの？
You're moving, Mai-chan?
（麻衣）未定…
Undecided.
（祐子）とほほ
スラマッパギはスルーですか
Do you even say selamat pagi?
It can't be helped, I guess I'll let the phrase rest for today.
しかたない  このワードは
今日でララバイしますか
Yukko.
（麻衣）ゆっこ
（祐子）あっ
Selamat malam.
TL note: Indonesian for "good evening".
スラマッマラム
Mai-chan, you should say selamat pagi there!
麻衣ちゃん
そこは スラマッパギだろっ
ウフフッ
What language is that?
（みお）それ 何語？
H-Homeroom will begin.
（桜井(さくらい)先生）あっ
ホ… ホームルーム 始めます
Um, when I came to school this morning, this was in the shoe rack...
えっと 今朝 学校に来たら
これが げた箱に入っていました
Did anyone put this in there?
誰か入れた人は いませんか？
U-Um... If there is anyone who knows about it, please tell me, okay?
え… ええと
もし 何か知ってる人がいたら
教えてくださいね
Mio-chan, I wonder who did that?
みおちゃん  誰だろうね？
あんなことするの
Maybe it's a prank?
イタズラなのかな？
It might be something unexpected
like a student who likes the teacher...
意外と先生のことを
好きな生徒だったり
I don't think they would leave a Maitreya statue though.
それで弥勒菩薩(みろくぼさつ)は ないよ
But, well, it's not like I don't understand
people who have unachievable aspirations.
まあ でも そういう
かなわない人への―
憧れの気持ちは
分からなくもないよ
Yeah, it's that, right?
うん  あれでしょ？
Like the way you feel about Sasahara-senpai.
みおちゃんが
笹原(ささはら)先輩を思ってるみたいな
Y-You idiot!
バ… バカヤロウ！
Where am I?
（なの）ここ どこだろう？
（なの）わあ… ああ
I have to get home!
帰らなきゃ
I'm sure the professor is worried,
はかせも きっと心配しているし
七輪 つけっぱなしで危ないし
and leaving her with the charcoal stove is dangerous.
Eh?
これ 下りられない！
I can't get off!
えっ？ お箸がない
Eh?
My chopsticks are gone!
One of my shoes is gone as well!
つっかけもない
ううっ どうしよう…
What should I do?!
わあっ
My hand's gone!
腕がない！
ああっ ロボだってバレちゃう
Now it'll be exposed that I am a robot!
Here it goes.
いくよ
Wonderful
Thank you for the food.
ごちそうさま
If you don't finish up quick, the bell for fifth period will ring.
ほら 早く食べないと
５時間目ＬＬだよ
Huh?
あれ？ ウインナー
好きじゃなかったっけ？
You didn't like sausages?
フッフッフッフッフ
Saving the most delicious food for last in a lunch box is fundamental.
お弁当の最後は―
一番おいしいやつにするのが
基本ですよ
Then, I can finish by saying: "It's delicious".
そんで“うまい！”と言って
締めくくるんです
（みお）ふうん
Well then, here goes... I'm going to eat it!
そいじゃあ ひとつ
いっただっきまーす
Nichijou 02
ぐううっ
ぐうっ ぬおお！
のわあっ
抜けたっ！
It came out!
Not yet!
まだだあ！
It's over!
終わったあ！
Not just yet!
まだまだあ！
（祐子）１つ
One...
...two...
２つ
...three.
３つ
Safe!
セーフ
ああ！ アウトだよっ
You're out!
（祐子）
フフン ヤダなあ みおちゃん
３秒ルールだよ ３秒ルール
No way, Mio-chan!
It's the three-second rule, the three-second rule.
No, you were already out way before that!
いや なんかもう
いっぱい いっぱいアウトだよ
（中之条）えへへ
It's delicious!
うまい！
Yukko really is an idiot.
（みお）ゆっこは バカだなあ
First comes rock, next comes paper, rockscispaper doesn't count,
（はかせ･なの）
♪ 最初はグー  その次 パー
rock paper scissors!
Yes!
はーい
えいっ
（校長）ええ 皆さん
おはようございます
Good morning, everyone.
Spring has come and a new year has started,
春になり新しい年度が
始まりましたが―
but the cold days are still continuing.
まだまだ寒い日が続きますね
In my case, I have it twice as cold as everyone else.
私は 皆さんの
倍は寒いんですけどね
Nichijou 03
Anyway, make sure you don't catch a cold...
とにかくカゼをひかないように
いいですか
これは校長先生との約束です
This is a promise with your principal, okay?
If you don't listen, then I'll be...
皆さんが言うことを
聞かなかったら―
校長先生は…
...transferred to a different school, on principle!
ほかの学校の校長先生に
なっちゃいますよ
Mio-chan, Mio-chan.
みおちゃん みおちゃん
What?
何？ 話してると怒られるよ
He'll get mad if you talk.
Say, doesn't the principal notice that his jokes are way too old?
あのさ  校長って―
自分のギャグが古すぎること
気付いてないのかな
He must know best of all that his jokes aren't received very well.
毎回 受け入れられて
ないことぐらい―
本人が 一番
分かっていると思うんだけど
うーん どうなんだろうね
I wonder about that...
（祐子）もしかして
Could it be that he knows his jokes aren't received well,
受け入れられてないことを
知りながら―
and is putting on a show of even more
effort to the young people nowadays?!
なお努力する姿勢を―
現代のすれた若者に
見せているの… かも
If that's true, then this principal...
そうだとすれば
この校長かなりの手だれ！
...is pretty skilful!
Mai-chan?!
（祐子）麻衣ちゃん？
Mai-chan is...?!
麻衣ちゃんが！
Could it be because of that old geezer gag?
まさか あのオヤジギャグが？
（祐子）しかも 麻衣ちゃんが
Above that, this is the first time I've ever seen her laughing so hard!
こんなに笑ってるところ
初めて見たよ
All right!
よし！ ここは ひとつ
This should do it!
麻衣ちゃ！
Mai-chan!
（祐子）あっ なぜだろう
Why is it?
If I said it here now, I feel like I'll lose everything.
今 ここで言ったら
すべてを失いそうな気がする
ゆっこ
Yukko.
Sorry.
（麻衣）
ごめん やっぱ 何でもない
Never mind, actually.
I guess, until she notices...
（麻衣）
やっぱり 気付くまで…
...I won't grab it.
取るのは やめよう
Squid
Well then, next is a talk about student guidance from Sakurai-sensei.
（教頭先生）では続いて
桜井先生から生徒指導のお話です
Sakurai-sensei, please.
桜井先生 お願いします
Um, Sakurai-sensei?
（高崎(たかさき)先生）あの… 桜井先生
（桜井）はいっ
Yes!
I'm sorry, I'm Sakurai from student counselling...
すいません 生徒指導の桜井です
うっ すいません
I'm sorry... Eh, ah...
（桜井）うう  やっぱり
こんな人数いると緊張する
I get really nervous when there's so many people.
No good, this is no good!
ダメダメ こんなんじゃ
I can't always stand and look like a helpless teacher...
いつまで たっても
理想の教師に近づけないんだから
I have to say what I need to say properly!
言うべきところで
ビシッと言わないと
I know!
そうだ！
Do you often see a goat on the school grounds lately?
最近 校内で
ヤギをよく見かけるんですが―
Let's not take goats with us to the school grounds!
ヤギは 学校には―
あまり持ってこないように
しましょう
What's wrong...
（笹原幸治郎(こうじろう)）
ヤギの… ヤギの何が悪い
What's wrong with goats?!
Going to school on a goat isn't prohibited by the school rules,
ヤギで通学するのは
校則違反ではないであろうが！
am I right?!
Eh, ah... that is...
（桜井）えっ ああ その…
Mio-chan, isn't that Sasahara-senpai?
（祐子）みおちゃん
あれ笹原先輩じゃない？
Eh, really?
へええ　そーお？
ううう  ヤ… ヤギを許可します！
No... I'll permit goats!
It's rejected, rejected!
（立花(たちばな)みさと）
却下よ！ 却下　ド却下よ
Absolutely rejected!
There's no way it's okay to bring a goat to school!
ヤギなんか
持ってきていいわけ ないでしょ
You can say that, but Tachibana Misato...
（笹原）
そうは言うが 立花みさとよ
Why must I rush about on my own two legs?
なぜ私が 二本足で
スタコラ歩かねばならんのだ
First of all, the heir of the Sasahara family...
大体 笹原家の長男というのは…
What's that about the heir of the Sasahara family?
なにが笹原家の長男よ！
You guys are just normal farmers!
あんたんち
普通の農家でしょうが
So?
だから何だ
長男が長男と言って
何が悪いのだ
What's wrong with the heir saying he's the heir?
Heh, so Sasahara-kun's family are farmers.
（フェッちゃん）ふえっ
笹原君ちって農家だったんだ
（ウェボシー）
なんか だまされた気分
I feel like I've been deceived.
So that goat at the bike rack was Sasahara-senpai's.
（みお）あの自転車置き場のヤギ
笹原先輩のだったんだ
Riding a white goat, Sasahara-senpai will come and pick me up!
白ヤギに乗った笹原先輩が
私を迎えに…
ア ハッピー ニューイヤー
A happy new year!
ミ… ミートゥー
M-Me too!
（みお）Ｑ～！
Mio-chan!
（祐子）わっ みおちゃん！
Using a cellphone while riding a bicycle is very dangerous,
自転車に乗りながらの携帯は
大変 危険です
let's stop doing that!
絶対 やめましょう
And also, one last thing...
それと最後に…
This morning, a Maitreya statue was in my shoe locker!
今朝 私の げた箱に
弥勒菩薩が入っていました
I don't think these kind of pranks are good.
こういうイタズラをするのは
よくないと思います
Excuse us, passing through...
すいませーん 通りまーす
A Maitreya statue.
（麻衣）弥勒菩薩…
うわあっ 麻衣ちゃん
急に立ち止まらないで
Mai-chan!
Don't stop suddenly!
Ah, this thing again?
（麻衣）ここら辺
デジャブかもしれない
It might be déjà vu.
Who did it?!
誰が やったんですか？
怒らないから手を上げてください
I won't get mad, so raise your hand!
You'll all stay here until he comes forth!
出てくるまで
今日は このまま朝礼ですよ
Who was it?
（男子生徒１）誰だよ
（男子生徒２）お前 出ろよ
You go forth.
I'm sorry, I heard it was Sakurai-sensei's birthday, so...
（校長）いやあ  桜井先生が
誕生日だと聞いていたもので
I see, a Maitreya statue is no good, eh?
いやいや そうですか
弥勒菩薩はダメですか
With good intentions on your birthday, a present.
I'll imagine that you don't need a Maitreya statue.
The principal.
With this, the morning assembly is finished.
（教頭）以上で朝礼を終わります
Thank you very much for your work up until today, Principal.
校長先生　今日まで
ありがとうございました
Deputy principal?!
教頭！
Fire Alarm
Push Hard
Button
This fire hydrant button has a really strong magical pull that makes you want to press it, doesn't it?
この消火栓のボタンって
すごく押したくなる魔力があるよね
Indeed.
（祐子）そうだね
クックック
What if you try pressing it?
（祐子）押してみたら？
The alarm didn't go off last time I pressed it.
それ前 押したら
音とか鳴らなかったし
Eh?
えっ ホント？
Really?
Fire?
（男子生徒１）えっ 火事？
（男子生徒２）ウソ！
No way!
What should we do?
（女子生徒１）
どうすんの？ これ　逃げんの？
Are we going to run?
Everyone!
（男子生徒３）
みんな とりあえず校庭に出るぞ
For now, let's go to the court!
What the hell are you pushing me aside for?!
（男子生徒４）てめえ
なに 人の背中 押してんだよ
You're the one pushing me!
（男子生徒５）お前が押したんだろ
What're you saying?
（男子生徒４）
何 言ってんだ？ 大体 お前
前からムカついてたんだよ
Besides, I've always hated you!
Stop it!
（女子生徒２）やめなよ
人が死ぬかもしれないのよ
We might end up dying here!
Let's get out of here first!
（男子生徒６）まずは逃げろ
ケンカは それからだ
Leave the arguing for later!
Um...
（死神）あのお
（死神）あの すいません
ＫＹ(ケーワイ)って何でしょうか？
I'm sorry, but what is "KY"?
TL Note: "KY" is short for "Kuuki Yomenai" meaning "unable to read the atmosphere".
（死神）あの…
（女性）キャアー！
Um...
What could "KY" be?
ＫＹって何なんでしょう？
I'm sorry, please tell me about "KY"!
すいませーん
ＫＹについて教えてくださーい
Help me, someone!
（男性）助けてくれえ
（死神隊長）おい！
Hey!
Oh, Captain... What could "KY" be?
あっ 隊長
ＫＹって何でしょうか？
It's referring to you.
お前のことだよ
Second grade Class B, Sasahara Koujirou.
（富岡(とみおか)先生）２年Ｂ組 笹原幸治郎
Important Matters and Things to be done
Please come to the staff room immediately to Tomioka.
至急 職員室の
富岡のところまで来るように
Important Matters and Things to be done
It's true, it's not violating the school rules... But a goat?
（富岡）確かに
校則違反ではないがな
ヤギは ないだろ ヤギは
Can't you do something about it?
なんとかならんか？
If you don't like to walk,
徒歩がイヤなら
自転車でもいいんだぞ
you could come by bicycle... Just as long as it's not a goat.
ヤギでなければ
Sir.
御仁
It's Tomioka.
（富岡）富岡だ
Tomioka.
富岡
Add sensei to it.
（富岡）先生をつけろ
Sensei.
先生
Can you call him Sasahara Kojirou, and not goat?
ヤギではなく―
笹原コジロウと
呼ぶわけにはいかないか？
He is a goat for now.
今は ヤギだ
Nichijou 04
My name is Shinonome Nano.
（なの）
私は東雲なのっていいます
I'm a robot created by Professor, whom I live with.
一緒に住んでいる
はかせが作ってくれたロボットです
Professor seems to be doing some kind of research,
はかせは 何らかの研究を
しているらしく―
and is at home all day.
一日中 家にいます
I spend my days while also helping out the professor.
私は その お手伝いをしながら
日々 過ごしています
Professor!
はかせ  牛乳 温(あった)めまし… た！
I warmed up the milk-
（なの）
秀でた機能は ありませんが
痛覚は あるようです
I don't have any special features, but it seems like I can still feel pain.
Nano, what's wrong?
（はかせ）なの どうしたの？
は… はかせ
小指が… 小指があ！
Professor!
My little toe...!
My little toe was...!
ココッ ココッ コココ… 小指
カカカ カカカ カカカ…
Y-Your l-little toe was...!
（なの）ハアッ
（はかせ）ポン！
はう
With this, you should be fine for now.
（はかせ）とりあえず
これで大丈夫だから
Eh?!
I don't have any special features,
（なの）
秀でた機能は ありませんが
小指が取れるそうです
but it seems like you can take off my little toe.
Professor, what's this key for?
（なの）はかせ
このネジは何なんですか？
I didn't turn it?
ああ 回したことなかったっけ？
Ah yes, it turns sometimes.
（なの）あっ はい
たまに回りますが
（はかせ）フフッ これは
こうやって回すとねえ
You turn it like this.
Ah, what's going on?!
（なの）うわあっ 何ですか？
（はかせ）フウ シュパー！
I'm sorry, I'm full of special features.
（なの）すみません
秀でた機能 満載です
See, it's something interesting, isn't it?
ねっ 面白いでしょ？
Could it be that you made the key just for this?
もしかして…
これだけのためにネジを？
Yup.
そうだよお
Could it be that you made the key just for this?!
もしかして
これだけのためにネジを？
Yup!
そうだよ！
Take it off, please!
外してください
No way!
（はかせ）ヤダー！
（なの）ええっ
Eh?!
Because it's cute.
なぜならカワイイからです
Remove it from my back, please!
（なの）リアルに外してください
Eh... But it's cute...
ええ カワイイのに
I want to be more normal.
私は もっと普通がいいんです
I want to sit on a chair like a normal person,
普通の人みたいに イスに座ったり
寝返りを打ったりしたいんです
and turn over when I sleep.
With this, I can't even go to school.
（なの）これじゃあ
学校にも行けないです
I would've been okay with not being a human-type robot at all.
いっそ人型ロボットでなければ
よかったのに
Nano...
（はかせ）なの…
I-It's just a lie!
な… なんて ウソですよ ウソ
A lie!
Don't take it seriously, Professor!
もう イヤだなあ  はかせは
Then take it...
（はかせ）じゃあ 取って
（なの）え？
Eh?
Go and win the Akutagawa Award for Literature!
芥川(あくたがわ)賞 取って
Why?!
なんで？
Win the Akutagawa Award!
Shinonome Institute
（はかせ）芥川賞！ 芥川賞！
Every day is like that.
（なの）そんな毎日です
Where am I?
（男子生徒）ここ どこだろう？
Hello!
This is Nano-chan's big toe!
My capacity is one gigabyte.
I would've preferred to be a bit bigger...
The next episode of Nichijou is episode two.
Narration   Katsura Reiko
Please look forward to it!
（親指）こんにちは
なのちゃんの足の親指です
容量は１ギガです
もうちょっと
欲しいところですよね
次回の「日常」は
第２話です お楽しみに